So now that we've understood why and what is the need of gold based planning, we've understood
basics around gold based planning in terms of mathematical understanding or time value
of money.
Let me actually help you understand how do you plan for somebody's gold, right?
So we are taking this small case of a client who's 30 years old, okay, has a child which is
three years old, and three major goals.
Child education planning at 18 years from now, child marriage planning, 22 years from now,
and retirement planning 30 years from now, right?
So let's say, let's make a note of this so that we are clear, we are saying we're talking
about a client who's looking at child education planning at the end of the 18th year, marriage
planning, 22 years from now, and his own retirement planning at the end of the 30th
year from now.
Now you will see categorically, I've not written any numbers here, because you will not
have numbers given to you like this, and you will have to actually figure out these numbers
having a discussion with the client, how, what do I mean, let's kind of understand.
So let's say, for example, I'm talking about education plan, okay, so we are saying you
will not have numbers given to you like they are given to you in an exam, you'll have
to have this discussion with the client.
So let's say, now you understand that the client wants to client for the child's education
at the end of the 18th year from today.
The first question that you will have to ask the client is, you know, suppose if the client,
suppose if your child has to do post graduation today, how much money do you think are you
willing to spend for the child's education today, right?
So depending on whether he wants to make the child a doctor, an engineer, or want to do an
MBA, he might have, of course, it is very difficult to predict what will happen at the end of
the 18th year, but this is exactly where this conversation comes into picture, is how much
money do you think you are willing to spend today if your child has to do post graduation?
Let's say the client says that I am okay with spending roughly 10 lakh rupees in today's
term, if my child has to do a post graduation today, now what you ideally have to understand
is, this 10 lakh rupees today that the client is willing to spend will not be 10 lakh rupees
today is because education cost is increasing each year and this 10 lakh rupees today that
the client is willing to spend is going to become much higher 18 years from today and if you
want to plan for the child's education, the first thing you will have to figure out is how
much is the cost going to be 18 years from today of this 10 lakh rupees. So you will have
to take an assumption that let's say education cost will increase at 7% each year. The client
is willing to spend equally valent of 10 lakh rupees today, how much will this 10 lakh
rupees become 18 years from today because 18 years later that is the amount of money which
the client really has to spend, not 10 lakhs. So first is we have to figure out if 10 lakhs
is what the client is willing to spend today, we are saying the cost is increasing at 7%, how much
will this 18 lakh rupees become at 10 to the 10th year. So what data do we have? So we have
the present value which is 10 lakhs which is what the client is willing to invest today,
we have the rate at which education is going to become expensive which is 7%. We also have the
income where we need, where we need this is 18 years, where we need this money for graduation,
or post graduation. So now we are first going to figure out the future value, where we have to first
understand how much will this 10 lakh rupees actually become and how much do I actually need at the
end of the 18th year for education. So I have to find ff, so I click fx, search ff, so what's my rate?
7%, what's my n per 18? I don't have PMT, what's my present value?
minus 10 lakhs, you can either write it down, I've just linked it.
Type is not applicable because I'm neither finding PV nor am I,
nor do I have, sorry, neither am I finding SIPs, nor do I have SIPs that I'm talking about.
So type does not matter, I click enter, I get the future value. Now I'm saying the course
for which I'm willing to spend 10 lakh rupees today and if it is increasing each year,
this course is actually going to become roughly close to 34 lakh rupees in the future.
33 lakh, 79,932. You can actually square this up to 34 lakh, that's not matter.
The point that I'm trying to raise is, the first thing you will have to understand is,
10 lakhs is not what you want to save, you want to save 34 lakhs is because 18 years from today,
the value of the course that you want to do today is going to be 34 lakhs. Step two,
now I know that at the end of the 18th year, I need let's say 34 lakhs,
let's say because I have 18 years and the client's risk profile allows me to invest in equity,
I'm assuming that I will be able to generate 12%. See if you've not done asset allocation,
you don't know what return to consider here. So I'm assuming you would have done asset allocation
by now and hence you know that you are going to invest let's say 80% in equity and 20% in debt
and hence you are considering 12% return. So if 12% is the return that you will be able to generate 34
lakhs is what you want after 18 years, you will have to help the client understand how much SIP
will the client have to do every month. So we'll have to find the PMT, the only challenge is,
I want the answer in months, I want the answer in months here because I have to tell monthly
SIP to the client, but the rate is per year, so I will have to divide this by 12 and I'll have
to multiply this by 12 to bring everything into months like we've done it in the past. Now let's find
the PMT, so I want to find the PMT here, so I'm going to go to the search bar search for PMT,
here's the PMT, now what's my rate, my rate is 12%, but that is per year, so I will divide it by 12
because my PMT is in months, I want the answer in monthly SIP, so I'll have to convert everything else
into months, 18 years into 12, PV, am I doing lump sum investment right now, nothing, so I'll leave that
I'm going to do I want in the future, I want 34 lakhs, you can either take 33, 79, exact or 34
you're gone, type I'm going to keep as one because I want to inculcate the habit of doing SIPs at the
beginning of the month, so I'm going to take type as one, here's the answer, 4, 4, 4, 2, 4, 4, 4, 4, 2,
which means that if currently I'm willing to spend 10 lakh rupees for my child's education,
which is going to become 34 lakhs in the future, I want to actually gather 34 lakhs after 18 years,
at 12%, I'll have to do an SIP of 4, 442 rupees, so for my child's education I'll just write it down
so that we don't forget, for my child's education, I will roughly have to do an SIP of 4,500
clear, so I will have to do 4,500 rupees of SIP for my child's education, now over here I have very
systematically helped the client understand why 4,500, I'm not randomly going to the client and
telling the client do a 5,000 BPS thing, I hope is where you will understand why the client will do 4,500
and most probably stick for those 18 years to make sure that the client education goal is taken
exactly the same way we have to do child marriage plan exactly the same way, so child's marriage
planning is after how many years, so we are saying child's marriage planning is after 22 years,
we asked the client exactly the same question, suppose if your child was supposed to get married today,
how much money are you willing to spend, let's say the client says I'm willing to spend 25 lakhs,
now you know that the child is not getting married today, so 25 lakhs is what you are willing to spend
today, inflation is going to make it more expensive right, 22 years later the expense is not going to be
25 lakhs, so the first step is exactly like we did in education, you will have to figure out
how much is the equivalent of 25 lakhs, 22 years later, you will again take an assumption that
inflation will increase at 7% and now find that if 25 lakhs is going to increase at 7% each year,
how much will my child marriage cost actually turn out to be at the end of the 22nd years from today,
right, we will do the same thing, so over here my present value is let's say how much,
25 lakhs is what I'm willing to spend, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, inflation is 7%, so I'll keep the rate as 7,
this is 22, right, let's solve, I want to find the future value,
here's the future value, so what's my rate, 7% inflation, what's my n power, 22,
PMT is not given, what's my PV, how much is the cost of
marriage today, minus 25 lakhs, it's a cost so minus, type does not matter neither am I given PV,
sorry PMT nor am I finding PV, I click enter, I get the answer,
suppose if I'm willing to spend 25 lakh rupees on marriage today, it's equivalent, 22 years later
is going to be 1.1 crore, so the client does not have to plan, the client does not have to plan for 25
lakhs for daughter's marriage, the client has to actually plan for 1.1 crore, because 25 lakhs
is going to be equivalent to 1.1 crore after 22 years, so now my question is very simple,
if the client at the end of the 22nd year wants 1.1 crore and basis your asset allocation,
you think 12% is okay and that can be generated, find the SIP that the client we have to do,
right, the same thing, we have future value, we have future value here, 1.1 crore, 22 years is
when I want the money at 12% I will find the SIP, so I want to find the PMT, how do I do it,
simple yours PMT, what's the rate, the rate is 12%, but I will divide it by 12, because I want
the answer in months, SIP is in months, no, so I want the answer in months, so divide it by 12,
and per is how much, 22, 22, into 12, because again remember PMT is in months,
PV, do I have something to invest, write down lump sum, no, so I will leave it blank,
Fe, how much do I want, 1 crore, 10 lakhs, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and I am going to put the type as 1,
is because I want to inculcate the habit of beginning of the period of investment,
I click enter, I will have to do 8,500 rupees of SIP for child's marriage,
8,500 rupees of SIP for child marriage, again I am sure you will agree and concur with me
that we have not randomly told the client, now the client notes that I will have to do 8,500,
if I am willing to do a 25 lakh work of marriage, kind of marriage today because it is going
to cost me 1.1 crore when the child is actually ready for marriage, the last thing,
what we will try and figure out is retirement, the client wants to plan for his retirement,
which is after 30 years, now you will have to ask one question to the client, removing EMI,
what is your yearly family expense, so let us say the yearly family expense today is 3 lakhs,
hypothetically right, is all the information you need and you can plan for clients again,
how they sent it out, so if the client's yearly expense today, exo, after EMI is 3 lakhs,
client wants to make sure that I can make the same standard of living made available,
after retirement when I don't have any expenses, so the first step you will have to figure out is,
if 3 lakhs each today's expense, how much will this expense become at retirement when the client
is supposed to retire, because unless you don't know how much money do you need each year after retirement,
how will you plan for retirement, so the first step is to figure out how much money do I need after
retirement right, absolutely, so the first step is if today's expense, if today's expense is 3 lakhs,
okay, and the client wants to retire 30 years from today, you will have to figure out,
if today's 3 lakhs expense will become how much after 30 years, so again we consider,
let's say inflation is 7%, so we are saying 3 lakhs is today's expense, it is going to increase
at 7% each year for 30 years, please figure out how much is going to be the expense of the client
for year, when the client is going to retire at the end of the 30 years, so what do we do, simple
and we are saying that the current expense is minus 3 lakhs each year,
okay, let me do it here so that I don't have to format sales, so we are saying that the current
expense of the client is minus 3 lakhs each year, client is going to retire after how many years,
30, and the rate at which expenses are increasing is 7%. We want to figure out when the client actually
retires at the end of the 30 year, when the client actually retires at the end of the 30 year,
how much is going to be this expense equivalent to today, so we will find the future value,
future value, let's say what's my rate, 7%, what's my end per 30 years, do I have PMT,
no I'm not talking about anything happening year on year, I'm trying to figure out if my expense
today is 3 lakhs, how much will that expense be at the end of the 30 year, so PMT is nothing,
PV is minus 3 lakhs, and because we are not talking about PMT, there is nothing to do with type here,
so forget about the type and I'll click on it, now I'm saying that the expense of 3 lakhs,
the expense of 3 lakhs that we saw today, we are going to become equal to 22 lakhs,
80, 3000 rupees after retirement, so even if you don't want to increase our standard of living,
even if you don't want to increase our standard of living at all, the client will require
22 lakhs, 83,660 or whatever that money is, after retirement as long as he survives,
so let's say the client after retirement is going to survive, let's say for 20 years,
so now we are saying for 20 years, now we are saying for 20 years, the client will require how much,
22 lakhs, 83,000 or 83,000 and not right in 676, so the client will require a PMT because the client
will require it each year, 22 lakhs, 83,000 rupees each year for 20 years after retirement,
now tell me where will the client get, 22 lakhs, 83,000 each year after retirement, so the client has
to get 23 lakhs each year after retirement, how will the client get 23 lakhs each year after retirement,
the client will only get 23 lakhs each year after retirement, if ad retirement client has accumulated
some purpose, so now we will try and understand that if the client wants 23 lakhs whatever each year,
after retirement for 20 years, how much purpose does the client need, I hope you are with me so far
understand what I am trying to say, so I am saying let's say the client is 60, the client is going to
survive up to 80 and client requires 22.83 lakhs each year, up to 80 but for this the client will have
to have some money you are at 60, so while you look at 60 to 80, 60 is the present value and 80 is the
future value, I hope you are all with me and understanding what I am trying to tell you, so from 60 to 80,
the client needs 22.83 each year, correct but for the client to get 22.83 each year, the client will
need some money at 60 which gets invested and the client will get 22.83 each year,
right, so while I am trying to solve 60 to 80, 60 is the PV and 80 is the FP, so now what is the data
that I have, the data that I have is, my P and T is 22 lakhs, 83,000 for 20 years between 60 to 80,
I have to figure out how much money do I need at 60, so that I get 22.83 each year from 60 to 80,
now there is a small complication here which I want to explain to you, so that you all understand
why and what am I doing in the next step, right, so we are saying let's say the client is 60 at 80,
each year the client will require 22.83, right, figure out how much money should be deposited at 60,
so that the client gets 22.83 each year of who 20 years, for that you will have to deposit here,
so whatever you deposit will get invested at some rate, let's say that rate is 5%,
because after retirement you will not want to take risk and interest rates will keep falling over
a period of time, so why you are at 60, the interest rates will already be much lower, so 5%,
so how much money do you have or should you have which gets invested at 5%, so that you get 22,
83 each year of who 20 years, there is one small catch, the catch is does 22 with 83 stay constant each
year does inflation not affect the client just because the client has retired the answer is right,
so the client wants 22, 83 in the first year, the client would want slightly more in the next year,
then slightly more in the next year, then slightly more in the next year to make sure that the client also
takes care of inflation, now this mathematically can be written as you minus whatever the inflation rate
is going to be, from the return and do the entire calculation at that minus rate,
again I am not going into technicality but there is a formula you have to find the real rate of return,
but we are not appearing for any exam, so you do not have to find the real rate of return using
some formula, you can do this mathematics simply as the return that I am going to get 6280 minus
the inflation that is going to be and I am going to do my entire calculation at 2%, now when you do
this entire calculation at 2%, you take into consideration that 22.8 3 will increase by inflation
and you will get that increased amount also, what do I mean just give me a moment I will try to explain
to you, so 20 year is my end for, rate I have figured out is 2%, I want a PMT of 22, 83, each year
find the present value that I will need so that I am able to do this, so let's solve this very
simple, I am going to delete all of this so that there is no confusion, okay, so we are saying
how much do I need every year and saying 22, 83, what is the rate 2%, what is the period, this is an
assumption that I will survive up to 20 years, I want to find the peak, so I will click on PV,
what's my rate 2%, N per 20, PMT, I have 22, 83, type is going to be 1,
is because after retirement where your income has stopped, right, you want money at the beginning
of the period, so period is always 1, future value, I don't need any money after I die at the end
of the 20th year, right, so future is 0 or PV blank, which means you will need 3.8 crore,
now what does this mean, pay attention, if you want 22.83 lakhs, plus inflation, plus inflation
each year for 20 years, right, at 5 minus 3, 2%, you will have to today accumulate 3.8 crore
when you are 60, so if, so how does this work, at 65, I have 3.8 crore, I invest 3.8 crore at 5%,
so in the first year I will withdraw 22.83, in the second year also I make 5% only,
but because I want more, I will withdraw 22.83 plus 3%, I hope you are with me and understanding
what I am trying to say, right, you will withdraw plus 3%, and you will keep doing that till 20th year,
right, by minusing this 3% and doing the entire calculation at 2%, I made sure that this happens,
I get 22.83 in the first year, I get 22.83 plus 3% in the second year, then I get that value plus 3%
in the third year, so on and so forth till 20th year, right, if there is slight test of the confusion,
just go back, rewind the last 5 minutes and you are near, right, so now I am saying that if I want
this entire thing to happen, I will need 3.8 crore at 60, I am 30 today, at 60, I will need
3.8 crore, because of my asset allocation, I am telling you that we will be able to generate how much
12% return, tell me the SIP, okay, why my writing is like this, tell me the SIP, I want to do,
at future 60, I want 3.8 crore, rate is 12%, that is this determined by my asset allocation,
my n power is 30 years, because I am 30 and I want money at 60, tell me the SIP, I will have to do
to make sure that I am able to get 3.8 crore, right, what do you do, very simple, click PMT,
watch your rate, 12% divided by 12, okay, let me not write it like this, it might confuse
a couple of 1, 12% divided by 12, why because I want the answer in months, n power is how much
30 into 12, PV, I don't have any money that I have saved right now, future, how much do I want,
3.8 crore, and I will write the type as 1, we have discussed this multiple times,
so if I want, if my rate is 1%, my number of periods for which I have to do investment is
30 into 12, 360 months, and my future value that I want is 3.8 crore, and type is 1, what is my PMT,
there was some error, let's do it again, rate is 12%, divided by 12, 30 into 12 is the period,
I want 3.8 crore, and type is 1, I click enter, the SIP that I will have to do is 10,765,
let me delete all of this, 10,765, so let me copy this here so that there is no confusion,
what is the SIP, I will have to do for my retirement, 10,765, so let me write 10,750,
just ignore the percentage, which means, now hear me out very well,
if I am 30 years old, I am going to retire at 60 and survive at 80, if I invest 10,750,
if I invest 10,750 here, for 30 years, at maturity, how much do I get, 3.8 crore,
and if that 3.8 crore here is invested at 5%, then for the remaining 20 years, I get 22.8,
22.8 lakhs in the first year, that's the 61st year, in the 62nd year, I get 22.83,
plus 3%, so on and so forth, in a way, that up to the 80, 80th year, the value becomes 0,
which means, if I go to this client, I can help this client very practically understand that for child
marriage, he has to shell out 4,800, sorry, education for child marriage, 8,500, and for his
own retirement, he has to shell out 11,750, and that's the total SIP that he should do, I hope,
this entire discussion, case study around how to plan for child's marriage, child education
and retirement is absolutely clear, wherever you are stuck, please just go back, remind the video,
that's the advantage of online learning, remind the video, try and understand it again,
if you don't understand, just write to us and we'll help you understand again,
of wherever you are stuck. I hope you understood this case study, case study, absolutely
thank you so much, I'll see you on the other side of the road.